hi I'm Steve Clemens and I have a
question if Israel's war has gone Way
Beyond self-defense to the point of
making the Gaza Strip itself completely
unlivable why is the Biden
Administration supporting it let's get
to the bottom
line in less than 3 months Israel has
killed nearly 1% of the Palestinian
people living in the Gaza Strip to put
that in perspective 1% of the population
of America would be more than 3 million
people that's like wiping out an entire
State like Arkansas or Nevada and so far
there's just no end in sight hundreds of
innocent civilians mostly women and
children are killed by Israeli forces
daily and almost 100% of the people
living there are now displaced that's
100% they're desperate they're hungry
they're cold Israeli and US officials
are acting as if the Palestinians should
blame themselves because Hamas carried
out a surprise attack in October that
killed about 1,200 Israeli soldiers and
civilians but when a country wages a war
it usually has a specific outcome that
it's looking for so what's the endgame
for Israel today we're talking with one
of America's most influential thinkers
John mimer professor of political
science at the University of Chicago and
author of the Israel Lobby and US
foreign policy as well as most recently
how States think the rationality of
foreign policy John it's terrific to be
with you today thank you so much for
joining us
um you wrote a piece this week death and
destruction in Gaza in which you said
that we've reached a point where there
is simply no meaningful military purpose
in Israel's war tell us what you
meant well when it comes to what Israel
is doing in Gaza you have to distinguish
between going after
Hamas and punishing the civilian
population and when we talk about
punishing the civilian population we're
talking about killing murdering huge
numbers of civilians displacing them
from their home starving large chunks of
the Palestinian population inside Gaza
and so forth and so on these are
basically war crimes I don't think there
are many people who would dispute that
Israel has what we call the right to go
after Hamas Hamas attacked Israel
Israel's going after Hamas that's not
really a contested issue for the most
part but what the Israelis are doing is
they're going far beyond going after
Hamas and they are inflicting massive
pain and Punishment on the civilian
population and in my opinion this should
be unacceptable to decent people all
over the world and the idea that the
Biden Administration is not only
sanctioning this but supporting it it's
very important to understand that the
Israelis could not conduct this
punishment campaign without support from
the United States they need American
military weaponry and furthermore they
need American diplomatic support and we
are giving that to them so we are as as
deeply involved in this disaster this
humanitarian disaster as the Israelis
themselves are do you find that there's
a worry that America's on the wrong side
of this no I think there's widespread
support in inside the American Body
politic uh for uh uh the Palestinian
civilian population I mean I don't think
there's any question that lots of people
think that what the Israelis are doing
to the civilian population is deeply
wrong there's no question there uh a lot
of people won't voice their opinion on
this issue publicly uh and that's in
large part because they fear that the
Israel Lobby will Target them and that
will do damage to their career uh
there's all sorts of evidence that
people on college and university
campuses are self- censoring for fear of
the Israel lobby but even there it's
clear that there's just widespread
support uh for uh the Palestinian people
and widespread criticism of what Israel
is
doing what would you be advising
President Biden early on in this
conflict if you were trying to advise
him or the Israelis how to respond after
October
7th well I think in the beginning uh
Biden should have gone to Great Lengths
to tell the Israelis to make sure that
uh they executed a measured response and
that they did not
overreact and he should have made it
clear that uh he would support the
Israelis against Hamas uh I mean he had
no choice there for sure
but he also should have made it clear to
the Israelis that uh if they went after
the civilian population the way they are
going after the civilian population uh
the United States would go to Great
Lengths to throttle uh Israel's attempts
uh to murder huge numbers of civilians
that's what he should have done we
should be on the other side of the
divide with regard to this campaign this
bombing campaign that the Israelis are w
in uh against uh the Palestinian
civilians and by the way it's not just a
bombing campaign uh the Israelis are
trying to starve uh large numbers of
Palestinians to death they've made that
very clear it's not like I'm making this
up the Israelis themselves say that this
is exactly what they're doing uh if you
look at what the Israelis are saying
about uh the Palestinians how they
describe the Palestinians talking about
them as human animals uh and so forth
and so on and then you you talk you
listen to what they're saying when they
talk about what they intend to do uh to
Gaza you know they talk about flattening
leveling it eradicating it uh you see
very clearly that they are purposely uh
targeting uh the civilian population and
they are doing massive amounts of
killing John if killing 1% of the
population so many innocent people isn't
a red line for the neighborhood for
Egypt for Jordan for other nations
around there for the United States are
we all just in a in a performance act
right now saying Israel please don't
harm civilians please limit what you're
doing but we're watching we're just
helpless and just watching a horrible
scene just unfold with no real
leverage yeah I think that's exactly
what's happening I mean just to talk
about the United States we have uh the
potential uh to bring this uh bombing
campaign to an end we have huge
potential leverage over Israel there's
no question about it but it's almost
impossible for any president including
President Biden obviously uh to use any
of that leverage and uh the end result
is we can say that we hope Israel uh
will limit this campaign and do
everything it can to minimize civilian
casualties but we don't do anything
concrete or at least we haven't done
anything concrete up to this point to
prevent uh the Israelis from killing
large numbers of civilians and by the
way it's not just the Americans the
Europeans uh are doing nothing
themselves uh the Germans and the
British their behavior is especially
egregious on this front but even in the
Arab world uh you don't see uh the
Elites in the Arab world uh doing very
much to put an end to this and in fact
there's all sorts of evidence that in
the Arab world it's pressure from below
uh that is largely motivating the elites
to criticize what the Israelis are doing
uh and it's a tragic situation and it is
quite remarkable in the year
2023 uh that uh the Israelis are able to
get away with this what do you think
Israel
wants uh if not a two-state solution oh
it's very clear to me what Israel wants
and we're talking here about the uh the
government they want to ethnically
cleanse uh Gaza and they want to
ethnically cleanse uh the West Bank the
problem that the Israelis face Steve is
that inside greater Israel and greater
Israel includes Gaza the West Bank and
green line Israel there are
approximately uh
7.3 million Palestinians and there are
approximately 7.3 million Jews so you
have rough equality in the number of
Jews and Palestinians inside greater
Israel and that means you can have a
democratic State and if you don't want a
two-state solution then what are you
going to do well up to now the answer is
quite clear Israel has turned into an
apart time state it is an apartheid
state and the Israelis understand that
over the long term this is probably not
viable we all know what happened to
South Africa can Israel exist over the
long term as an apartheid state and you
want to remember that groups like Human
Rights Watch uh Amnesty International
Bellum and so forth and so on have
labeled Israel as an aparti state so
they want to get out of that situation
and the best way to do that from their
point of view is to ethnically cleanse
uh the ga the Gaza Strip and the West
Bank much like they ethnically cleansed
large parts of green line Israel in 1948
and much the way they cleansed large
parts of the West Bank in
1967 the problem is that they have not
been able to do that and the United
States much to its credit has at least
said that it will not uh countenance
Israel ethnically cleansing Gaza but
we'll see what happens there the
Israelis are punishing the civilian
population in Gaza in large part in my
opinion to drive them out but they have
not been successful so far I want to
play For You John a clip um of Danny
Danon Israel's former ambassador of the
United Nations in 2019 and something he
said about what's behind Israel's goals
listen this is a deed to our
land he's holding up the Bible basically
the Old Testament to say this is the
deed to our lands in the United Nations
and I'm just asking you as sort of an
analyst to say if that's what we're
working with and America is allied with
that how does this ever get to a
different point than just an ongoing
horrible convulsive
ulcer it doesn't I mean this is where we
are and by the way if you look at the
demographics inside of Israel the people
who are most likely to make the
argument uh that was just made uh that
you know the Bible is Israel's deed uh
to owning all of Greater Israel uh the
people who are most likely to make that
argument are the ultra orthodox and the
old Orthodox now form about
133% of Israel's
population uh but over time their
numbers are going to increase greatly up
to the point where in about the year
2050 uh you're going to have about 30%
of Israel close to onethird of Israel
will be uh Ultra Orthodox and that's
because the birth rate among old
Orthodox women is so high uh this means
that the argument that Danny Denon was
just making is going to become heard
more widely in Israel it's not only
going to be people like him it's going
to be more and more Ultra Orthodox Jews
making that argument uh so this argument
is simply not going
away let me ask you about responsibility
to protect because right now in
Washington we have a couple of things
tied together uh American support of
Ukraine uh in in the Russia War a lot of
particularly um those in on the progress
agressive side of the foreign policy
we're talking about r2p the
responsibility to protect as one of the
animators of Americans support Ukraine
where are they with regards to the
Israel Gaza conflict and the
responsibility to protect
Palestinians I I hear remarkably little
from them uh there are all these people
who have been talking uh for years now
about the importance of
r2p uh the importance of Protec ing
human rights and you would expect all of
them to be uh loudly proclaiming that
what the Israelis are doing is
unacceptable and that the United States
has a moral responsibility to put an end
to all of this killing of civilians of
Palestinians but H you hear very little
from these human rights proponents and
uh from human rights groups uh inside
the United States uh the silence is
actually quite amazing you know when I
watch polls and what's going on it's
very clear that younger generation
Democrats particularly Democrats of
color but it's really broad SWA of
younger voters in the Democratic party
are very very uh uh frustrated with Joe
Biden's position on Israel Gaza and you
see a collapse in their support and when
you interview them and do focus groups
right now they say there's nothing
that's going to bring them to support
Joe Biden there's a more General problem
at play here uh and that is that Israel
has lots of support among people your
age and my age but once you begin to go
down uh and look at younger cohorts it's
a very different story there's a Harris
Harvard poll that came out very recently
that says that if you look at people
between the ages of 18 and 24 you survey
them and you ask them this question was
Hamas Justified in killing Israeli
citizens on October 7th we're not
talking about killing the military we're
talking about killing civilians in other
words was Hamas justified in what it did
on October 7th
51% of people in the United States
between the ages of 18 20 18 and 24 say
that Hamas was justified this is
stunning and then if you look at people
between the ages of 25 and 34 25 and 34
48 48% say that Hamas was justified in
what it did on October 7th so you see
that Israel has a real problem and of
course this problem manifests itself on
college campuses and that's why the
lobby is working overtime now to try to
shut down criticism of Israel uh at
universities and colleges and then uh
his last last interview Henry Kissinger
did with Axel Springer CEO Matias dner
Kissinger said that the problem
societies like the United States and
Germany had was letting in so many
refugees so many people from other
groups because they then become agents
for those other groups for those other
identities and it just seemed to me one
of the most
remarkable inhumane comments about the
importance of others outside like
Palestinians you know I'm interested in
that tension about race and identity
inside pluralistic societies right now
and whether or not we're trying to
wrestle that decency out of
ourselves well I would come at this from
a slightly different perspective uh I I
I don't like the Kissinger argument uh
about bringing uh people from different
ethnic backgrounds uh or different
countries into the United States the
United States is an immigrant culture I
think that's a wonderful thing and I
have no problem with bringing immigrants
into the United States I think it's
what's made bringing immigrants into the
United States in huge numbers in the
19th century is what made this country
great and uh it's will will keep this
country powerful into the future so I
have no problem with immigration the
issue for me is uh how to think about
realist Behavior
versus moral behavior when you think
about how a state should act in the
International System and I fully
understand that states have a
deep-seated interest in security
competition for the purposes of
maximizing their chances of surviving
and I fully understand that states
sometimes do ruthless things to other
states for good strategic reasons
okay but at the same time there has to
be a moral Dimension that underpins how
States behave towards other states and
as long as there are no sort of
strategic reasons or realist reasons for
behaving ruthlessly States should go to
Great Lengths to act in a moral way I
have no problem making that argument and
I think in the case of what's going on
inside of
Gaza
uh there is no strategic reason for
Israel to destroy Palestinian Society to
kill huge numbers of civilians it it
just doesn't make good strategic sense
and I believe it is morally wrong uh so
this is why I am so deeply opposed to it
I think there's no question that Israel
has the right I use that word Loosely it
has the right to go after Hamas Hamas
attacked Israel Israel can go after
Hamas and I understand that as Israel
goes after Hamas there's going to be
collateral damage civilians are going to
be killed this happens in Wartime it is
regrettable but it is a basic fact of
life it's very different than purposely
targeting uh civilians uh for the
purposes of inflicting massive pain and
Punishment on them
and again this has no strategic logic
there's there's no sort of realist
reason for doing this and therefore I
think it's deeply
wrong do you see any chance at all
America will in any time you know close
to now turn off that tap it's a rare
occasion when the United States puts
course of Leverage on Israel especially
when it comes to dealing with the
Palestinians uh and that's because any
government including the Biden
Administration understands full well
that if we are to get rough with the
Israelis or we were to get rough with
the Israelis the Israel Lobby would come
after the administration hammer and
tongue and the administration doesn't
want that especially since we're moving
into an election year are we going to be
complicit do you think in the
possibility of equations that are in
fact ethnic
cleansing well there's not a growing
clamor I mean there's no question that
uh this is a
powerful uh motive uh on the right
inside of Israel and inside of the
United States uh the United States has
made it clear uh the US government the
Biden Administration has made it clear
that that's
unacceptable uh the question is what
happens if the Israelis just do it
uh when could argue that you know we're
marching towards the point where there
may be massive ethnic cleansing uh if
this bombing continues and the Israelis
continue to prevent uh water and food
and Medicine uh from coming into Gaza in
large enough amounts uh it could be that
the Palestinians begin to move out of
Gaza and that the Israelis uh do
everything they can to facilitate that
just hard to say how this plays out
moving forward but the Israelis could
just do it and just ignore uh what the
Biden Administration is saying about
what is that is not acceptable so it
remains a real possibility and as I said
to you before you want to understand
that the Israelis basically have two
choices here whether to continue
operating as an apartheid state and to
continue keeping Gaza as basically a
giant open air prison or to ethnically
cleanse Gaza and the West Bank at the
same time if they can now they would
definitely prefer to do that and uh the
the Administration has said you can't do
that but again how that plays itself out
uh remains to be seen well the Biden
Administration uh keeps trying to say
that it wants the ground war to end by
Year's End I don't see that happen I see
this as a story we're going to be having
to continue to focus on for some time
John I hope you'll come back and keep
sharing your perspectives as this
evolves thank you so much for joining us
professor John Mir shimer of the
University of Chicago thank you Steve
for having me on the show so what's the
bottom line Israel's forces have
destroyed more than 100,000 buildings in
Gaza that's on top of the killing of
thousands of women and children
Innocents and it implies a different
objective in this war according to at
least one Israeli cabinet official the
emphasis is on quote unquote damage not
accuracy this conflict the babies buried
in the rubble of collapsed apartment
buildings the destruction of bakeries
that provide bread the parading of
captured Palestinian men and underwear
all of it is going to be seared into the
minds of not only Palestinian victims
but all of us there's no moral High
Ground here there's no sense that
innocent Palestinian people matter in
any equation they were a burden and a
new in the eyes of many in Israel
particularly settlers before October 7th
they're looked at as inhuman the US
government is complicit in the horrors
we are seeing it's just nonsensical it's
an orwellian Circle where America thinks
it can both be seen as a legitimate Ally
of palestine's interests while it sits
coldly on the side of Israel's
untempered war machine that only cares
about damage and that's sadly the bottom
line
[Music]